Guide to the Henry Sherman Family Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Henry Sherman family papers
1795-1926
MS 832
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
2.5
(2 boxes, 2 folios)
The papers are made up almost entirely of scrapbooks assembled by Henry Sherman, his wife and four of his children. The scrapbooks offer vivid documentation of their lives in the period 1850-1900 in Washington, D.C. with correspondence, photographs, drawings, clippings and memorabilia of all kinds.
Sherman, Henry, 1808-1879
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Peter Tillou, 1974.
Biographical / Historical
Henry Sherman, who died in Washington, D. C., March 28, 1879, was the third son of Josiah and Hannah (Jones) Sherman, of Albany, N. Y., where he was born March 6, 1808.
He spent a part of the first year after graduation in the Princeton (N. J.) Theological Seminary, and then took up the study of law in the Yale Law School, returning in 1832 to his home in Albany, and there entering his profession. He soon removed to New York City, and while practicing there published in 1841 a "Digest of the Law of Marine Insurance," which ran through several editions. In 1843 he also published a "Governmental History of the U.S.," for use in schools. In 1850 he removed to Hartford, Conn., and there published (1858) a work on slavery and (1860) an enlarged edition of his History. In 1861 he removed to Washington, and was employed until 1868 in connection with one of the bureaus of the Treasury Department. In 1868 he resumed the practice of his profession in Washington, in which he continued until his death (which occurred, after a three weeks' illness, from erysipelas), being at that time of the law firm of Sherman & Atlee. Mr. Sherman was a personal friend of President Lincoln, who on the morning before his assassination tendered him the Chief Justiceship of the Territory of New Mexico, his commission was afterwards sent him by President Johnson, but he resigned the office very soon.
He was married, Sept. 20, 1843, to Miss Anna Amelia, daughter of Michael Burnham, Esq., publisher of the New York Evening Post. She survives him with three of their five children.
Yale College Obituary Record, 1870-1880. pp.343-344
Scope and Contents
The papers are made up almost entirely of scrapbooks assembled by Henry Sherman, his wife and four of his children. The scrapbooks offer vivid documentation of their lives in the period 1850-1900 in Washington, D.C. with correspondence, photographs, drawings, clippings and memorabilia of all kinds.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Families; Students; Southern States; United States -- Social life and customs; Washington (D.C.); Albums (Books); Lawyers; Mitchell, Elizabeth Sherman; Sherman, Ada Elizabeth, d. 1875; Sherman, Anna Amelia Burnham, d. 1897; Sherman, Anna Burnham; Sherman, Ellen Minott, d. 1901; Sherman, Henry Roger, 1864-; Sherman, Henry, 1808-1879; Sherman, Josiah, 1770-1832; Sherman, Roger Minott, 1773-1844; Sherman family; Yale College (1718-1887). Class of 1829; Yale University -- Students
- Inventory
  - Scrapbooks and other items by Henry Sherman, 1809-1879.
    - Scrapbook No. 1
      - 1795-1877. Family correspondence, 1795-1803, among Roger Minott Sherman, his brother, Josiah, and sister, Betsey Mitchell [Mrs. John Mitchell?], including a letter from Roger M. Sherman at Yale College, 1795, and an account of Sherman family history. The book continues with letters from Henry Sherman to his father, Josiah, and Yale memorabilia relating to the class of 1829, including bills, clippings and programs. For the period 1833-1877, the scrapbook contains social items (invitations, valentines, programs), verses by Henry Sherman, and family and business correspondence following his career from Albany to New York to Hartford and finally to Washington, D.C. Also included are clippings, reviews and correspondence relating to his book, Slavery in the United States, first published in 1858. (Box 1)
    - Scrapbook No. 2
      - 1836-1847. Scrapbook of literary extracts from contemporary newspapers. "The scraps were collected by Miss Anna Mary Mandall of Albany, now Mrs. Robert Minturn of New York. She presented them to me about a fortnight before she was married, on condition that I have them neatly pasted in 'a Scrap Book', to which I assented and received them. Some months after, I became acquainted with Miss Mary Camp, a beautiful 'girl of sixteen,' at Albany from Sackett's Harbour. She requested me to write a piece of original Poetry in the Album. I consented on condition that she would paste 'some scraps' I had in a book for me, to which she promised & thus I secured the fulfillment of my engagement with my fair friend and the donor of them. So this volume commemorates the kindness of two female friends." [Signed] Henry Sherman. (Box 2)
    - Scrapbook No. 3
      - 1834-1876. A scrapbook made up largely of documents: degrees, awards, letters of appointment, copyrights, together with related correspondence and clippings. Among the items is a copy (in English translation) of a letter of thanks from Lajos Kossuth to Sherman and others in Connecticut for their financial support (1852). (Box 3)
    - Scrapbook No. 4
      - 1842-1878. A scrapbook of newspaper articles written by Henry Sherman, covering the pages of his Yale College algebra notebook, dated 1826. (Box 4)
    - Manuscript (1840)
      - 1840. Ms. The Law of Marine Insurance/ Being/ A full report of all the cases/ adjudged in the Court/ of the State of/ New York/ Commenced June 2nd - 1840/ by/ Henry Sherman/ Counsellor at Law. [published under the title: An analytical digest of the law of marine insurance, containing a digest of all the cases adjudged in this state...New York, 1841] (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Scrapbooks of Anna Burnham Sherman, daughter of Henry Sherman.
    - Scrapbook No. 5
      - 1876-1916. A scrapbook largely made up of letters relating to her mother's illness in 1897 and letters of condolence upon her death. Also included are several pencil sketches, unidentified, and miscellaneous letters and clippings, 1876-1916, generally reporting marriages and deaths of members of the family or friends. (Box 3)
    - Scrapbook No. 6
      - 1850-1897. A scrapbook kept jointly with her sister, Ellen Minott Sherman, beginning with the correspondence of Anna Amelia Burnham Sherman (their mother) with her mother, Elizabeth Burnham, 1850, and continuing with school mementos of Anna and Ellen Sherman (1860s), invitations to entertainments, private and public, programs, clippings, pencil sketches and photographs. Included also are numerous mementos of Vassar College, 1867-1870, collected by Ellen Sherman during her years there. Subsequent pages are covered with cards and invitations to social and cultural events in Washington, D.C., 1870-1899, miscellaneous correspondence, clippings, mementos, including photographs of Ellen Sherman's school in Washington, D.C. The book concludes with letters of condolence to Ellen Sherman on the death of her mother in October 1897. Scrapbooks of Anna Amelia Burnham Sherman, wife of Henry Sherman. (Box 2)
  - Scrapbooks of Anna Amelia Burnham Sherman, wife of Henry Sherman.
    - Scrapbook No. 7
      - 1844-1895. Correspondence, newspaper clippings, pencil sketches and photographs. A large portion of the album is devoted to letters of condolence on the death of her daughter, Ada Elizabeth, September 9, 1875. The other items document her life in Hartford, Conn. and Washington, D.C. (Box 3)
    - Scrapbook No. 8
      - 1837-1897. Letters patent for an improvement in the rotary steam engine, issued to Roger M. Sherman, 1837-1839. Letters patent to J.J. Sherman for improvement inballoons, 1860. Clippings and memorabilia relating to Henry Sherman, her husband, and school exercises and other mementos of her son, Henry Roger Sherman, 1874-1880. Many engravings of prominent political and literary figures, a pencil drawing by A.A.B. Sherman and miscellaneous correspondence. (Box 3)
  - Scrapbook of Ada Elizabeth Sherman, daughter of Henry Sherman
    - Scrapbook No. 9
      - 1862-1875; 1878-1894. Clippings, calling cards, invitations, two Japanese prints dated 1867, a diploma, 1873, school exercises, genealogical charts, photographs and assorted memorabilia, including an Indian arrowhead. The latter part of the book is devoted to letters of condolence on her death in 1875. At the very end are a few letters addressed to her sister, Anna B. Sherman, with family news, 1878-1894. (Box 4)
  - Scrapbooks of Henry Roger Sherman, son of Henry Sherman
    - Scrapbook No. 10
      - [1914-1916]. "Scrapbook of newspaper accounts of fires and things of interest to H. Roger Sherman" -Handwritten title on the cover. With 3 photographs of fires laid in. (Box 4)
    - Scrapbook No. 11
      - Scrapbook of fires in Boston, New York and elsewhere, ca. 1925. Scrapbook of Ellen Minott Sherman, daughter of Henry Sherman (Box 4)
  - Scrapbook of Ellen Minott Sherman, daughter of Henry Sherman
    - Scrapbook No. 12
      General note
      See also Box 2, Scrapbook 6
      - 1896-1901. Clippings, poetry, correspondence, concluding with letters of condolence to Anna Burnham Sherman on the death of Ellen Sherman in 1901. (Box 4)
        General
  - Miscellaneous Papers
    - Pencil sketches of landscapes, 1836; sketch of Grant's Cottage, Hartford, Conn., undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Sherman, Henry Roger. Correspondence, 1926, from the War Department. Headquarters First Corps Area. Office of the Quartermaster, Boston. (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Memorabilia (Box 1, Folder 5)